<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true testimony from the people of God (who by the world are called Quakers) of the doctrines of the prophets, Christ, and the Apostles, which is witnessed unto, by them who are now raised up by the same power, and quickned by the same spirit and blood of the everlasting convenant which brought again our Lord Jesus from the dead ... / by M.F.</title>
            <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41070</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15690841</idno>
  <idno type="VID">104408</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240914964</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36435</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15690841</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104408)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1592:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true testimony from the people of God (who by the world are called Quakers) of the doctrines of the prophets, Christ, and the Apostles, which is witnessed unto, by them who are now raised up by the same power, and quickned by the same spirit and blood of the everlasting convenant which brought again our Lord Jesus from the dead ... / by M.F.</title>
                  <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104408:1"/>
            <p>A TRUE TESTIMONY From the People of God: (Who by the world are called QUAKERS) OF THE <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Prophets, Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Apostles,</hi> which is witnessed unto, by them who are now raised up by the same <hi>Power,</hi> and quickned by the same <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Everlasting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> which brought again our <hi>LORD JESUS</hi> from the dead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published for this End,</hi> (Viz.)</p>
            <p>That all sober minded People may see the <hi>Unity</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement</hi> of our <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Testimony,</hi> with the <hi>Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> of <hi>Jesus,</hi> and all the <hi>Holy Men of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the Difference between <hi>Us,</hi> and <hi>Them</hi> that have the <hi>Form</hi> of Words, but not the <hi>Power</hi> thereof.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Prove all things, and hold fast that which is good,
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Thes. 5.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Now we have received not the <hi>SPIRIT</hi> which is of the world, but the <hi>SPIRIT</hi> which is of God; for the spirit searcheth all things, yea the deep things of God,
<bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 10.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>M. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilson,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop at the sign of the <hi>Black-spread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Wind-Mill</hi> in <hi>Martins L'Grand,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:104408:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing that the day of the Lord is come, and he arisen in his Eternal <hi>Light,</hi> and is arising in the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Men, the place where his Throne and Scepter must <hi>Rule</hi> the <hi>Nations;</hi> and being that he is <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver</hi> to those who are under his Government, and is the supreme <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> in the Consciences: Now this being arisen and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested in this day of the Lord's Power, in the which he will make all his People willing and subject to him; and being that this hath been long obscured and covered with the thick vail of darknesse, and Cloud of Apostacy that hath been over the face of the Earth, and indeed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the hearts of men, and the onely cause and reason of this, hath been the Cup of Abomination and Fornication the Nations have drunk in the Worship of the Beast, upon which the Whore sits, which <hi>John</hi> saw (when he stood upon the Sand of the Sea) rise up out of the Sea, which all the world wondered after; insomuch, that <hi>Mystery Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> made all <hi>Nations</hi> drunk with the Cup of her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: And now the day is come, that <hi>Babylon</hi> is come up in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance with the Lord, and the Day of her <hi>Judgements</hi> is come, and the <hi>Vials</hi> are pouring upon the <hi>Seat</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Beast;</hi> and the darkness is expelling, and the Light is arising out of obscurity, and shining secretly in the hearts of People, where Gods appeareance and Manifestation is, where he writes his Law, and puts his Spirit in the inward parts, which is the new Covenant which he hath made with the House of <hi>Israel,</hi> and with the House of <hi>Judah,</hi> and which is also a Light to the Gentiles, by which they can do the things contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law, having the substance of the Law, which is Light, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their Hearts, their Consciences also bearing them witness of the Justice and Righteousness of the Law, when God comes to judge the secrets of their hearts by Jesus Christ, who is the end of the Law for
<pb facs="tcp:104408:2"/>Righteousness, and who is the Light that is given to be the salvation to the ends of the Earth.</p>
            <p>And now all people that comes to be guided by this Law, which is Light, they by so doing comes into Gods Covenant and Promise; and coming into this Light, and Covenant, and Spirit which God puts in the inward parts, here all people meet together, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Barbarian, Scithian, Bond</hi> and <hi>Free,</hi> in the Unity of the Spirit which is in <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> our Lord, in which they come to be all one in Christ; &amp; if they be Christ's, then are they <hi>Abraham's</hi> Seed, &amp; Heirs according to promise: Gal. <hi>3.29.</hi> This is the great Mystery that hath bin hid from <hi>Ages</hi> and <hi>Generations</hi> past, by reason of the gross Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness that hath covered men; and the great cause and reason of all this, hath heen because the <hi>Worship</hi> that hath been set up in the <hi>Nations,</hi> hath had its <hi>Foundation</hi> in the <hi>Darkness,</hi> &amp; the very root &amp; ground of it hath been Darkness it self, and the <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> thereof, have been <hi>Ministers</hi> of Darkness, and have not turned peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the darkness to the Light, but on the contrary have drawn them from the Light and Spirit of God within them, unto their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, Imaginations, Meanings, and Expositions of the Scriptures without them, and so have been building <hi>Babel</hi> in the many <hi>Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> which God is coming to confound; and it may be they have read a Chapter, and then turn and pervert it, and mix with it their own dark imaginations of their evil hearts; and again read a verse of a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and make an hours Discourse of what they had intended and hatched up in their minds (it may be) a week before. And thus they have fed poor people with Chaff and Husks; but the Lord is arisen in his mighty Power, with his Fan in his hand, and he is seperating the Chaff from the Wheat, and is gathering the Wheat into his Garner, and will burn up the Chaff with unquenchable fire.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Reader,</hi> in soberness and singleness of thy heart, read this following Treatise without an evil eye, and a prejudiced mind; and let the Truth of God have place in thy heart, and let the light of Christ in thy Conscience seriously judge and weigh the things therein contained, and (according to the Scriptures) prove all things, and hold fast that which is good; and look not at Men, nor at the Times as they stand in relation to men, for in so doing, the god of the world will blind the eye; but look at the Lord, and at his Truth, and eye his dealing and dispensation of his will according to his wisdom, and let
<pb facs="tcp:104408:3"/>him be thy fear, and let him be thy dread, and slight not thy Day of Visitation of his love; For truly the Lord whom we seek, will sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly come to his Temple, and who may abide the day of his coming? who will sift as a Refiners fire, and will be as Fullers Soap. Certainly he will plead with all flesh by Sword and by Fire, and bring into the <hi>Valley</hi> of <hi>Jehosaphat,</hi> and all flesh will be as grass, and the glory thereof as the Flower of the Field, when the spirit of the Lord blows upon it, because all People are Grass. It is not flesh and blood that can enter into the Kingdom of God, which he is now restoring unto <hi>Israel;</hi> it is that, that will pass the fire of his jealousie, and come through clear and pure, that will be accepted of in this his day; People have long made him serve with their sins, and wearyed him with their Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and their Worships and Services have been an abomination unto him; and the fear that hath been taught towards him, hath been by the precepts of men, and flesh and blood hath performed the Worship that should have been to him, and therefore hath there been no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Kingdom of God, but all have been kept back, and out of the holy City, though the Gates have stood open by Day, yet no unclean could enter, nor nothing that wrought abomination, or made a lye, for that is in the Night of darknesse, and is out of the Day where the Gates of the holy City stands open.</p>
            <p>And so now <hi>(Reader)</hi> these things being set before thee in love unto thee and to all people; slight them not, nor look not lightly over them; for if thou seriously consider and weigh them with that of God in thy Conscience, thou wilt sinde them truth, and according to the Scriptures of Truth: Therefore search and examine the following Treatise by the Scriptures and the Spirit of Truth, and thou wilt find that in thy own bosom which will answer to the Truth of what is here written. So to the Lord I commit thee, and to his witnesse in thee which will answer for his Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104408:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A true TESTIMONY,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To all the professed</hi> Teachers <hi>in the whole world, who go under the Name of</hi> Christians, <hi>and make a</hi> profession <hi>of Christ, who was offered up at</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>which the Scriptures declares of, whether they be</hi> Jesuits, Bishops, Priests, Protestants, Presbyters, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Anabaptists, <hi>and to all</hi> sorts <hi>of</hi> Sects <hi>and</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries <hi>whatsoever; This unto you all, to</hi> prove, <hi>or</hi> disprove <hi>the</hi> Doctrine <hi>of the</hi> QUAKERS, <hi>which is the same with</hi> Christ, <hi>the</hi> Apostles, <hi>and</hi> Prophets; <hi>which doth prove</hi> your Doctrine <hi>to be</hi> false, <hi>and out of the</hi> Doctrine of Christ.</head>
            <p>YOur <hi>Testimony</hi> which ye do bear of the coming of Christ (who are called Christians by Name) is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> because that there are Records left of <hi>Christs words</hi> which he spoke in the <hi>Mount,</hi> and which he spoke at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and at <hi>Samaria,</hi> and which he preached among the <hi>multitude,</hi> and the many Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that he wrought, and what he spoke to the <hi>Souldiers</hi> when he was <hi>apprehended,</hi> and what he spoke before the <hi>High Priest</hi> and <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> and what he spoke when he was <hi>upon the Cross.</hi> The Disciples having written of his Preaching, and of his Miracles that he wrought, and of his Sufferings, those Writings are your Testimony of <hi>Christ.</hi> And again, the <hi>Apostles</hi> after they had received the holy Ghost, and Power from above, when <hi>Christ</hi> was offered up and ascended, the <hi>Apostles</hi> having received <hi>his Eternal Spirit,</hi> and they going on in the work of God, converted thousands to the Faith, and did great and wonderful Works and Miracles by the Spirit of <hi>Christ</hi> which they had received, and they travelled up and down in several parts of the World, and turned Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104408:4"/>
               <hi>from Darkness to the Light, and from the power of Satan unto God;</hi> and there was a Record of their <hi>Works, Service,</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> which are called, <hi>The Acts of the Apostles,</hi> which do testifie of several remarkable <hi>Works, Actions,</hi> and <hi>Conversions,</hi> that were wrought by them through the <hi>Eternal Spirit.</hi> And after they had gathered several <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>People</hi> into the unity of the Eternal Light and Spirit of God, and had begotten many into the faith, which could bear witness in the Spirit of God of the Eternal Truth which they had received through the Doctrine of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Apostles</hi> when they were separated, and at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance from those <hi>Churches,</hi> they wrote several <hi>Epistles</hi> to the <hi>Saints,</hi> that were <hi>gathered</hi> and <hi>sanctified</hi> in <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> and made partakers of the precious Faith, &amp; such as were called to be <hi>Saints;</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> wrote not their <hi>Epistles</hi> to the <hi>world,</hi> nor to such as were <hi>not gathered</hi> by them, neither <hi>Iews</hi> nor <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> but <hi>to the Churches of Christ,</hi> sanctified in <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>to be Saints,</hi> of what <hi>sort</hi> or <hi>denomination</hi> soever they were, or <hi>went under,</hi> whether <hi>Corinthians, Ephesians, Romans, Galatians, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Apostacy</hi> and <hi>Darkness</hi> coming over, and the <hi>false Apostles</hi> getting up, being erred and gone from the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and turned aside from the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> of the <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> that the <hi>Apostles</hi> were in, and turning out of the <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>glorious Gospel</hi> which was in them, the darkness came over them, and the <hi>Antichristian Spirit</hi> entred in amongst them; for the Apostle <hi>John</hi> saw in his time, that <hi>Antichrist</hi> was come and entred into the World, whereby he said, <hi>He knew it was the last time,</hi> &amp; that there were many <hi>Antichrists</hi> already; &amp; he knew it was the time that Christ had prophesied of, <hi>That false Prophets should come in sheeps clothing, but inwardly were ravening Wolves,</hi> ravened and erred from the <hi>Spirit of Truth,</hi> which was <hi>in</hi> the <hi>true Apostles,</hi> and so did deceive many, that even darkness covered the face of the Earth, and all was lost, and the <hi>Beast</hi> rose out of <hi>the Sea,</hi> and out of the <hi>Earth,</hi> and all the <hi>World</hi> wondred after them, and <hi>fell down,</hi> and <hi>worshipped</hi> the <hi>Beast,</hi> and <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and his <hi>Power,</hi> and so all <hi>Nations</hi> were made <hi>drunk</hi> with his <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Fornication</hi> and <hi>Abomination;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104408:4"/>Yet this was not <hi>unseen</hi> nor <hi>undiscover'd</hi> before it came; For <hi>Christ</hi> prophesied of it, <hi>That false Christs and Antichrists would come in the later dayes, Wolves in sheepes clothing would come, and by their fruits you should know them, Mat.</hi> 7.15. And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Paul</hi> he knew <hi>that grievous Wolves would enter in amongst them after his departure, that would not spare the flock, Acts</hi> 20.29. And <hi>Peter</hi> he was sensible of <hi>false Prophets</hi> that was amongst the People, &amp; did also <hi>foretell</hi> of <hi>false Teachers that should privily bring in damnable Heresies, even denying the Lord that bought them;</hi> and he also saw, <hi>that many would follow their pernicious ways, and that through Covetousness they with feigned words would make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandice of People;</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> saw <hi>that in the last Dayes peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Times should come, that men should bee lovers of themselves, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a form of godliness,</hi> but <hi>denying</hi> the power; <hi>from such turn away,</hi> saith the <hi>Apostle;</hi> for of these sort are <hi>they which creep into houses</hi> (calling them Churches) <hi>and leads captive silly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, laden with sin, and led away with diverse lusts; ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth. Now as</hi> Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>and</hi> Jambres <hi>withstood</hi> Moses, <hi>so do these also resist the Truth: Men of corrupt minds, reprobate concerning the faith.</hi> And again, the same <hi>Apostle</hi> saith, <hi>That the time would come, when the people would not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts would heap to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves Teachers, having itching ears, &amp; they would turn away their ears from the Truth, &amp; should be turned unto Fables.</hi> Now all these seeing that this <hi>Apostacy</hi> would come, This is <hi>a certain testimony</hi> that it was <hi>to come,</hi> and <hi>is come,</hi> and hath over-spread the face of the earth <hi>since the Apostles daies,</hi> as hath been clearly manifested by the many <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Horns</hi> of the <hi>Beast,</hi> and of the <hi>Dragon;</hi> and the many <hi>Religions</hi> and <hi>Sects</hi> that have started up since the daies of the <hi>Apostles;</hi> and as one <hi>got up,</hi> another was <hi>pull'd down;</hi> And now <hi>the blind people</hi> that have been nursed up <hi>in blindness,</hi> and <hi>darkness,</hi> and <hi>ignorance,</hi> under this cloud of <hi>Apostacy;</hi> Now when that the <hi>Truth</hi> is manifested, and risen through this <hi>Darkness</hi> and <hi>Apostacy,</hi> and they seeing that the Scripture speaks of <hi>false Prophets,</hi> they say, the <hi>false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> are but com'd <hi>now;</hi> and they call the <hi>Spirit of Truth</hi> the <hi>false Prophet,</hi> because it <hi>bears testimony</hi> against the <hi>false worships</hi> in the World. But I would ask such people, which of these
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104408:5"/>
               <hi>Sects,</hi> or <hi>Heads,</hi> or <hi>Horns</hi> that have been up since the daies of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> which of them they look upon to be the <hi>true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Whether it is the <hi>Pope, Luther,</hi> or <hi>Calvin?</hi> or which <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (so called) or <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendents <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Anabaptises<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> for all these have <hi>been,</hi> and have had <hi>their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and have gotten the Writings of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Christ</hi> and the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o have all had <hi>the Form of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of godliness,</hi> according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> of the Apostle <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter,</hi> who said, <hi>There were false Prophets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the people, even as there should be false Teachers among them, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> should bring in damnable Heresies, and that they should receive the reward of unrighteousness, who have forsaken the right way, and are gone astray, following the way of Balaam, who loved the wages of unrighteousness,</hi> which the Apostle <hi>Jude</hi> said, <hi>Whose mouths must be stopt, who subvert whole Houses, teaching things they ought not for filthy lucre sake; who serves not the Lord Jesus Christ, but their own bellyes, and counts gain godlinesse.</hi> Now let all people <hi>search</hi> and <hi>read</hi> who these are, and whether these be the <hi>true Prophets,</hi> or <hi>the false?</hi> and whether these have not <hi>been,</hi> and yet are, <hi>in</hi> the time of <hi>Apostacy?</hi> for all <hi>Christendom</hi> (as its called) have had the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and professed <hi>Christ</hi> from the Declaration thereof, and not from the <hi>Spirit of Truth in themselves,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they have heard that there was such a <hi>Man</hi> which dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and that there were such men after him as the <hi>Apostles</hi> were; and they having their <hi>words</hi> and <hi>writings</hi> upon record, do make these a <hi>sufficient Testimony</hi> for them of their knowledge and worship of God, and so <hi>preach</hi> &amp; <hi>teach,</hi> and takes Texts out of these words, and adds thereunto their own <hi>Inventions,</hi> and so feeds <hi>poor ignorant</hi> people with these; and here hath been the Worship that hath been upon the face of the Earth all the time of the <hi>dark night</hi> of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy since the Apostles dayes. Now let any honest reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heart judge whether this can be a <hi>sure ground</hi> and <hi>true te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony</hi> for people, to trust their souls under <hi>such</hi> for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? for it was not <hi>Christ</hi> nor the <hi>Apostles</hi> practice to take o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Records &amp; Writings that had been spoken from others; <hi>but they spoke as the spirit gaue them utterance,</hi> and <hi>as the holy Ghost taught them, not with wisdom of words, but in the demonstration of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104408:5"/>the spirit and of power.</hi> Yet they will bring a <hi>Scripture,</hi> and say Christ took a Text when he spake of <hi>Esaiah's Prophesie,</hi> where he said <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me,</hi> &amp; <hi>he hath annointed me to preach, and to open the blind eyes,</hi> and <hi>to preach liberty to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; and when he had read these words, he closed the Book, and said, This day this Scripture is fulfilled in your ears,</hi> for it was <hi>he</hi> that the <hi>Prophet</hi> spoke of, who is the <hi>Annointing,</hi> and the <hi>Annointed, to preach glad tydings to the poor, and liberty to the captive,</hi> and to the <hi>opening of the blind eyes;</hi> but these <hi>blind Leaders</hi> leads the <hi>blind,</hi> but doth not open <hi>their eyes,</hi> though they can make the <hi>Scripture</hi> a <hi>covering</hi> for their <hi>false Worship;</hi> for let any one prove and try the <hi>Teachers themselves,</hi> and they are as <hi>blind,</hi> and as <hi>ignorant</hi> of their own souls, and as <hi>far</hi> from having a <hi>true testimony</hi> of <hi>assurance</hi> of their own <hi>salvation,</hi> as <hi>those</hi> they speak to, or pretend <hi>to teach:</hi> Now let people consider <hi>this,</hi> and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously <hi>lay it to heart,</hi> and beware how they trust <hi>their souls</hi> under such <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>teaching,</hi> who have no <hi>other,</hi> nor <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> Testimony then <hi>Records without them,</hi> which were given forth from the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in others; which spirit is <hi>Eternal</hi> and <hi>Infallible,</hi> which these Teachers of the World cannot <hi>in truth</hi> confess, but must (if they confess truth) <hi>utterly deny</hi> that they have any such <hi>spirit,</hi> as many of them have done already. How can these <hi>be true Teachers</hi> of people in the <hi>way of truth,</hi> which have not the <hi>spirit of truth?</hi> for if it be not an <hi>infallible spirit,</hi> it is a <hi>lying spirit,</hi> and not the <hi>spirit of Truth.</hi> Now let people seriously <hi>consider</hi> what they venture their souls upon; for it is not a <hi>deceitful lying spirit</hi> that will feed the soul, it's the <hi>spirit of life</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> that nourisheth the soul, and leads into all truth. Now here is the chief differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt <hi>them</hi> and <hi>us,</hi> They have the <hi>words</hi> and <hi>declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and the <hi>Apostles,</hi> declared from the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>life;</hi> and we have the <hi>spirit</hi> which these <hi>words</hi> words were <hi>declared from,</hi> not <hi>another,</hi> but the <hi>same eternal Spirit</hi> which they had, do we <hi>witness,</hi> and bear <hi>our Testimony</hi> of, the same <hi>Christ</hi> (and not of <hi>another</hi>) <hi>which witnessed a good confession before Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> and <hi>was crucified upon the cross at Ierusalem;</hi> This <hi>Christ</hi> which all the <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Christendom</hi> profess in <hi>words,</hi> do we bear <hi>testimony</hi> of in the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>life</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:104408:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it may be objected and said, <hi>How came you to this</hi> Spirit, <hi>seeing that you say, that darknesse and Apostacy hath been over the face of the Earth since the dayes of the Apostles, and that all Worships and Professions have been but from the Letter of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures without them; this is but an upstart Religion, how is it that you are attained to this that none are attained to in so many hundred years before? And are you wiser then all our fore-fathers? What is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all that is gone before?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ans.</hi> This <hi>Objection</hi> is against the <hi>unlimited Spirit</hi> &amp; <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>living God,</hi> which did <hi>foresee</hi> the <hi>Apostacy</hi> before it came; <hi>&amp; Christ</hi> and the <hi>Apostles</hi> did prophesie of it; for the same <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> might be against the Lord when he said unto <hi>Pharaoh, I even for the same purpose have raised thee up, that I might shew my power in thee, and that my power might be declared throughout all the Earth; therefore hath he mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he hardeneth.</hi> Thou wilt say then unto me, <hi>Why doth he yet find fault, who hath resisted his will?</hi> Nay, <hi>but oh man! who art thou that replies against God? shall the thing formed, say to him that formed it, Why hast thou made me thus?</hi> What if God (willing to shew his <hi>wrath,</hi> and to make his <hi>power</hi> known, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured with much <hi>long suffering,</hi> the Vessels of <hi>Wrath,</hi> fitted to destruction, and that he might make known the <hi>Riches</hi> of <hi>his glory</hi> on the <hi>Vessels</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> which he had before prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>unto glory;</hi> and this is the very case; The <hi>spirit</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> cannot be <hi>limited,</hi> but <hi>limits</hi> all according to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of his will, that he may make his <hi>power</hi> known.</p>
            <p>But further more, as to our particular, we answer, <hi>We recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not this spirit of Man, nor by Man, but by the immediate power and revelation of Iesus Christ, according to the work and operation of it in us;</hi> As the Apostle said, <hi>For when it pleased the Lord to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal his Son in the Apostle, he consulted not with flesh and blood, but went on in obedience unto the Lord:</hi> And so the <hi>same spirit</hi> that revealed the <hi>Son</hi> in the <hi>Apostle,</hi> revealed him <hi>in us;</hi> for we neither received it <hi>of man,</hi> neither were we taught it <hi>by man,</hi> but by the Revelation of <hi>Iesus Christ;</hi> for <hi>no man</hi> could teach it us, but who had the Revelation of <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> according as the Apostle said to the <hi>Romans, If the spirit of him that rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed up Iesus from the dead, dwell in you, he that raised up Christ from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104408:6"/>the dead, shall also quicken your mortal bodies, because that his spirit dwelleth in you, Rom.</hi> 8.11. And again, <hi>Know ye not that ye are the Temple of God, and that the spirit of God dwelleth in you?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. Now though these <hi>Scriptures</hi> bear <hi>testimony</hi> to the truth of this, yet these <hi>Scriptures</hi> are not our <hi>testimony</hi> only, for we have <hi>our testimony</hi> in the same <hi>spirit</hi> as was <hi>in them</hi> that spoke forth the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and these <hi>Scriptures bears testimony</hi> with <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> and so are <hi>in unity</hi> with the <hi>same Spirit</hi> which gave <hi>them forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is <hi>the Hope</hi> that we are to give an <hi>account of</hi> to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one <hi>that asketh</hi> with <hi>meekness</hi> &amp; <hi>fear;</hi> for God hath made <hi>known unto us</hi> the <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>glory</hi> of this <hi>Mystery</hi> amongst the <hi>Gentiles, which was Christ in them</hi> (and now in us) <hi>the hope of glory;</hi> and this is the same <hi>Christ which was offered up at Ierusalem once for all, through the Eternal spirit,</hi> and this is the <hi>HOPE which pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifies even as he is pure;</hi> which <hi>HOPE maketh not ashamed,</hi> but <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chors the Soul upon</hi> the <hi>Rock CHRIST IESUS;</hi> and the <hi>Apostles</hi> who had the <hi>Eternal spirit,</hi> are our <hi>forefathers:</hi> And this is not an <hi>upstart Religion</hi> which we <hi>are of,</hi> but a <hi>pure Religion,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled before God,</hi> which <hi>keeps</hi> every one <hi>that keeps in it, unspot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> of the world; Yet <hi>this hath been hid from ages and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons past, but now is revealed unto us by the spirit;</hi> which <hi>spirit</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have <hi>erred from</hi> in the time of <hi>Apostacy,</hi> and from this <hi>they do erre</hi> at this <hi>very day,</hi> and such counts the <hi>spirit within</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, and goes to <hi>Scriptures</hi> without them, and <hi>traditions</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> and teach <hi>those</hi> for <hi>Doctrine;</hi> and here is the <hi>Reason</hi> wherefore this Spirit and Revelation hath <hi>been hid</hi> so many <hi>hundred years,</hi> even because people have <hi>been erred</hi> from the <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>them,</hi> through which the <hi>Revelation</hi> is <hi>manifested,</hi> and they have been <hi>erred</hi> in their hearts; therefore the way of God hath not been known.</p>
            <p>Christ said to the <hi>Woman</hi> of <hi>Samaria</hi> when he was on the <hi>Mountain</hi> where <hi>Jacobs Well</hi> was, where the <hi>Jews</hi> used to <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> he said, <hi>They worshipped they knew not what;</hi> and he also said, that <hi>the time was coming that they should not worship at Jerusalem,</hi> (which was a place commanded of God for the Jews to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship in) <hi>nor in this Mountain;</hi> and he further testified, <hi>That God was a spirit, and that they that worshipped him, must worship him in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104408:7"/>spirit and in truth,</hi> saying, <hi>The Father was seeking such to worship him,</hi> for they only are the true Worshippers of God.</p>
            <p>Now I do ask all the <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Professors</hi> in <hi>Christendom,</hi> Where this <hi>spirit is,</hi> that God is to be <hi>worshipped in,</hi> if it be not <hi>in man?</hi> And how <hi>it is,</hi> or <hi>can be</hi> attained <hi>to,</hi> any otherwise than <hi>by the light of Christ Iesus with which he hath lighted every man that cometh into the world, in whom is life, and this life is the light of men?</hi> And where <hi>this worship</hi> of God <hi>in the spirit</hi> is <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> if it be not <hi>in man?</hi> And where <hi>Gods Throne is,</hi> (where the ancient of dayes <hi>doth sit</hi>) if it be not <hi>in man?</hi> And where the <hi>Scepter</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>swayed,</hi> which is a <hi>righteous Scepter,</hi> if it be not <hi>in Man?</hi> And where the <hi>King</hi> is that <hi>shall reign &amp; pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> whose Name shall be called, <hi>The Lord our Righteousness?</hi> And how and where must people come to <hi>worship God</hi> in the spirit, which <hi>denies</hi> the <hi>Light of Christ</hi> to be <hi>their Leader</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> and say it is <hi>Natural?</hi> and some say <hi>every one hath it not;</hi> and others say, <hi>It is not sufficient,</hi> and so they are all upon <hi>heaps,</hi> and in <hi>confusion,</hi> who believe not in the Light <hi>which Christ Iesus hath enlightened them withall,</hi> who is the Light of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man; so denying the Light, and being erred from it, are in darkness until now, and stumbles, and knows not whether they go.</p>
            <p>Christ saith, <hi>I am the light of the world, he that followeth me, shall not walk in Darkness, but shall have the Light of life:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain saith he, <hi>While ye have the Light, believe in the Light, that you may be the children of the Light: I am come a Light into the world, that whosoever believeth in me, shall not abide in darkness.</hi> Now I do ask any of the Teachers of the World, how any comes to see Christ any otherwise then <hi>by the light</hi> of the body, which he saith <hi>is the eye?</hi> seeing that he said to the <hi>Jews</hi> who talked with him, and he with them, <hi>They had not heard his voice, nor seen his shape; for he whom God hath sent, they believed not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may be the condition of the Priests of the World, and Teachers of the Letters, and they ought to own it, <hi>That they have neither heard his voice at any time, nor seen his shape;</hi> for how should they, when they deny <hi>the light</hi> of Christ that is <hi>in them</hi> to be their <hi>Guide</hi> and <hi>Teacher,</hi> which <hi>Christ hath lighted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104408:7"/>them withall, which is the Key of David, which opens and none shuts, and shuts and none opens?</hi> And he told the Jews, <hi>That they did search the Scriptures that did testifie of him, and in which they did think to have eternal life, but</hi> (sayes he) <hi>you will not come to me me that you may have life; I receive not honor from men</hi> (sayes he) <hi>I desire not that you should come to me as to give honour as from men, but that you would come that you might have life;</hi> but <hi>I know you, that you have not the love of God abiding in you:</hi> This he spoke to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that he said <hi>had not his word abiding in them,</hi> yet they searched the Scriptures, who did not <hi>believe</hi> in him, though he did many <hi>Miracles</hi> amongst them yet they <hi>persecuted</hi> him, and sought to <hi>kill</hi> him, and took up stones to stone him, <hi>who is given for a Covenant to the People, and for a Light to the Gentiles, that he may be the salvation to the ends of the Earth:</hi> And this is the <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Everlasting Covenant,</hi> the promise of God the Father, who hath said, <hi>Is it a light thing that thou should raise up the Tribes unto Iacob, and restore again the preserved of Israel?</hi> with whom the Lord hath said, <hi>I will make a new Covenant, I will write my Law in their hearts, and put my spirit in their inward parts;</hi> and by this Spirit and Light doth God <hi>teach his People himself;</hi> and all that comes to the leading and teaching of this Spirit, comes to the knowledge of the Lord, which shall cover the Earth, <hi>even as the waters covers the Sea;</hi> and to this Light did the Apostle turn people from the Darkness, and from the Power of Satan unto God. And by the nature of this <hi>Divine Light,</hi> did the Gentiles the things contained in the Law, which shewed the Work of the Law (of the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) written in their hearts, <hi>their consciences also bearing witness in the day when God shall judge the secrets of Men by Iesus Christ, according to the Gospel:</hi> And here the Apostle doth justifie the Gentiles, in that he saith, <hi>Not the hearers of the Law are justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but the doers;</hi> and their uncircumcision, <hi>which did the Law,</hi> he accounted circumcision, and said to the <hi>Jews, Shall not their uncircumcision judge your circumcision, which breaks the Law;</hi> &amp; he further saith, <hi>We are of the true circumcision, who worship God in the spirit, and rejoice in Christ Iesus, and have no confidence in the flesh; for he is not a Lew that is one outward, neither is that circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion which is outward in the flesh; but he is a Iew which is one inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104408:8"/>and that is circumcision that is of the heart, in the spirit, and not in the Letter, whose praise is not of men, but of God, Rom.</hi> 2. And this is the seal of the everlasting Covenant, that takes away the foreskin of the heart, and washes away the filth of the flesh; and here the knowledge of the true God is manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in man, where God shews it unto him, according to the Apostles Doctrine, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9.</p>
            <p>And when <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Mars-Hill,</hi> and saw the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Altar, with the inscription upon it, to the <hi>unknown God,</hi> he said, <hi>God that made the world, and all things therein, seeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, he dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, neither is he worshipped with mens hands, as though he needed any thing, seeing he giveth to all life and breath, and all things, and hath made of one blood all Nations of men, to dwell on the face of the Earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitation, that they should seek the Lord if haply they might feel after him, and find him, though he be not far from every one of us, for in him we live, move, &amp; have our being. Act.</hi> 17.24. Here the Apostle did not lead them out to the Writings and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of others without them, but he brought them to him <hi>in whom they did live, and move, and had their being,</hi> that so they might <hi>feel after him, and find him;</hi> for he said, <hi>He was not far from every one of them;</hi> and he brought them off the outward Temple which was made with hands, and said to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Ye are the Temple of the living God, as God hath said, I will dwell in them, and walk in them, I will be their God, and they shall be my People; and he that defiles the Temple of God, him will God destroy; for the Temple of God is holy, whose Temple are ye; and what, know ye not that your bodyes are the Temple of the Holy Ghost which is in you, which ye have of God, and ye are not your own, but you are bought with a price; therefore glorifie him in your body, and in your spirit, which are God's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Apostle clearly demonstrates, that the bodies of God's People are his Temple, and God is the Spirit that is in them; and this is the <hi>Teacher</hi> and <hi>Preacher,</hi> which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle turns and brings People to, whom he teaches; he told the <hi>Romans that the Righteousness of Faith speaketh on this wise, Say not in thy heart who shall ascend, or descend; but what saith it?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104408:8"/>The word is very nigh thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart, and that is the word of Faith that we preach,</hi> saith the Apostle, (mark) <hi>How then</hi> (saith he) <hi>shall ye call on him on whom ye have not believed? And how shall ye believe on him of whom ye not have heard? And how shall ye hear without a preacher? For Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</hi> And this is the Word which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle preached, <hi>which is nigh, in the heart; which word opens the blind eye, and unstops the deaf ear;</hi> and they cannot hear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Word of Faith, by hearing of which, Faith comes; and none can hear without this Preacher, who is sent <hi>to bring glad tydings of good things;</hi> but this is not the Preachers of the Letter of the Scriptures without them, for they have prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched many hundreds of years, but <hi>the deaf ears are not unstop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped yet,</hi> nor <hi>the Blind eyes opened by their Preaching;</hi> and so the Scripture is now fulfilled which the Prophet <hi>Isay</hi> spake of, who saith, <hi>Bring forth the blind People that have eyes, and the deaf that have ears;</hi> And again he saith, <hi>They have Eyes, and see not, Ears, and hear not, hearts, and do not understand</hi> Isa. 43.10</p>
            <p>And the Lord saith, <hi>I will lay waste Mountains and Hills, and dry up all their Herbs; and I will make their Rivers Islands, and</hi> I <hi>will dry up the Pools; and I will bring the blind by a way they knew not, and pathes which they have not seen; I will make darkness Light before them, and rough wayes plain, and crooked things streight;</hi> them that comes into this Path and Way, must come from the blind Teachers of the World, who are Leaders of the blind, and keeps people in blindness and ignorance of God, and his Truth, who denyes the Light to be a sufficient Teacher, <hi>which is the Eye of the whole body, &amp; if this Eye be single, he body is full of Light;</hi> But with this eye they do not see, neither can they believe the Truth if it be declared unto them, except they come to the Light that doth manifest it in them. Now the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Peter</hi> directed those that he wrote to, <hi>to a more sure Word of Prophesie then that which he heard in the Mount,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. Which voice he did not know that it was within him; and therefore he directed them <hi>to a more sure Word then that was which he heard in the Mount, which Word was a Word of Prophesie,</hi> whereunto he said, <hi>they did well that they took heed, as unto a light that shined in a dark place, until the day dawned, &amp; the day-star arose in their hearts;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104408:9"/>this testimony of Jesus, the which is the spirit of Prophesie:</hi> This the Teachers of the World brings to blind people with, &amp; saith it the Scripture that the Apostle speaks of. Now let any that have but common reason judge, whether the Apostle was like to say, That the Scriptures were a more sure Word, then the Voice of God that was heard in the Mount, which said, <hi>This is my beloved Son, hear ye him;</hi> and that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>should be a light shining in a dark place,</hi> and that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures should be the <hi>day dawning, and the day-star arising in the heart:</hi> If people would but look into things, they might see their deceivableness; for the Apostle goes on with these words, saying, <hi>Knowing this first, that no Prophesie of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is of any private interpretation; for the Prophesie came not in old time by the will of man, but holy men of God spake as they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Ghost.</hi> Here the Apostle disswades them from looking at the Scriptures to be <hi>of any private Interpretation,</hi> or coming by the will of man, which is their whole work, to give their Meanings and Interpretations in their own Wills unto, which is wholly contrary to the Apostles Exhortation and Doctrine, who said, <hi>We have not followed cunning devised Fables, when we made known unto you the Power and the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were Eye-witnesses of his Majesty.</hi> And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> who was raised up by the Power, Spirit, and Voice of the Lord, who said, <hi>Arise and stand upon thy feet, for I have appeared unto thee for this purpose, to make thee a Minister and a Witness both of these things which thou hast seen, and of those things in which I will appear unto thee, delivering thee from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and from the Gentiles, to whom I now send thee to open the blind eyes, and to turn them from Darkness to the Light, Act.</hi> 26. And the Apostle goeth on bearing his testimony, having obtained the help of God, witnessing both to small and great, saying none other thing then that which the Prophets and <hi>Moses</hi> did say should come <hi>that Christ should suffer, and that he should be the first that should rise from the dead, and should shew Light unto the people, and to the Gentiles.</hi> And this was the Witness and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony which the Apostle held forth, who was a Minister of God. But these Teachers of the World deny and gain-says
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104408:9"/>this Doctrine; and the Apostle saith, <hi>Therefore seeing we have this Ministry, as we have received Mercy, we faint not, but have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the hidden things of dishonesty, not walking in craftiness, nor handling the word of God deceitfully; but by the Ministration of the Truth, commending our selves to every mans conscience in the sight of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 9.1. <hi>And if our Gospel be hid, it is hid from them that are lost, in whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds of them that believe not, least the light of the glorious Gospel of Christ, who is the Image of God, should shine unto them:</hi> See here, and behold how the Apostle <hi>recommended himself to every mans conscience in the sight of God;</hi> yet his Gospel <hi>might be hid to them that were lost,</hi> and was from the Light, and would not believe, <hi>which the god of the world had blinded their minds, least the Light should shine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them;</hi> and so it is the same still, our <hi>Gospel is hid unto such</hi> as believe not in the Light; <hi>For God who commanded the Light to shine out of the darkness, hath shined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jesus Christ;</hi> 2 Cor. 2.1.3.9. And if the Light of Christ shine not in their hearts, our Gospel is hid. And again he saith, <hi>Ye were some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times darkness, but now you are light in the Lord, walk as Children of the Light; for all things that are reproved, are made manifest by the light;</hi> Wherefore he saith, <hi>Awake thou that sleepest, and stand up, that Christ may give thee light, Eph.</hi> 5. And this is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage which the Apostle did declare, <hi>That God is light, and in him is no darkness at all; and if we say that we have fellowship with him, and walk in darkness, we lye, and do not the truth; but if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the blood of Jesus Christ his Son, cleanseth us from all sin,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5. This is the Message of the Minister of God; and the Apostle gave thanks unto God the Father <hi>which had made them meet to be partakers of the Inheritance with the Saints in light, who had delivered them from the power of darkness, and had transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them into the Kingdom of his dear Son.</hi> This is not a new Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, though it may seem so to many; because this <hi>Mystery</hi> hath been hid, and the Spirit of God which opens this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, erred from, and turned from, by those that have been Teachers of people; and not onely so, but even their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hath been, and now is, That none must look for, nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104408:10"/>expect <hi>Revelation</hi> nor <hi>Inspiration</hi> by the Spirit of God; and so they do what in them lyes, to stop this <hi>Current</hi> of Life and Spirit, which Christ Jesus the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all <hi>life</hi> hath set o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, who in the last day of the Feast stood up and said, <hi>If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man be a-thirst, let him come unto me, and drink; He that belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth on me, out of his belly shall flow Rivers of living Waters.</hi> And this he spake of the Spirit which these Teachers of the world would stop; the pourings of which Spirit is unlimited to <hi>Son</hi> or <hi>Daughter, Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile, Barbarian, Scythian, Bond,</hi> or <hi>Free, Time</hi> or <hi>Place,</hi> or <hi>Condition, but according to the good pleasure of his will, who is the Author and the Fountain of it;</hi> And all that are Ministers of God, and of the Spirit, it is their joy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire that people grow <hi>into the Light of Life;</hi> for they that are in the Light, the day of destruction shall not overtake them as a Thief, who are Children of the Light, and of the Day; And this is the desire of all the faithful in Christ Jesus, That they dwell and abide in the Light, where the fellowship is one with another, and where the power of God preserves and keeps from the pollutions of the World, and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Satan; which Power is made manifest by the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jesus Christ, who hath abolished death, and <hi>hath brought Life and Immortality to light through the Gospel, whose Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality dwells in the Light, where the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb is the Temple,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. And here the City comes to be known <hi>which hath no need of the Sun, nor of the Moon, to shine in it, for the glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the light thereof, and all the Nations of them that are saved shall walk in the light of it, and the Kings of the Earth shall bring their glory and honor to it, and the glory of the Nations shall come unto it, and there shall in no wise enter into it that which defiles, neither that which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth abomination, or maketh a lye, but they which are written in the Lambs book of life, Rev.</hi> 21. This is the great work which the Lord is working in this his Day, and the spiritual Building which he is rearing and setting up; and he hath put his hand to the work; and when he worketh, who can let it? Who hath resisted his Will? Who hath directed the Spirit of the Lord, or been his Counsellor? Or taught him? Of whom took he Councel? Or who instructed and taught him know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104408:10"/>and shewed him the way of understanding? <hi>Behold, the Nations are but as the drop of a Bucket, &amp; as the small dust of the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance before him; he taketh the Isles as a very little thing,</hi> Lebanon <hi>is not sufficient to burn, and the Beasts thereof for a Burnt-offering; it is he that sitteth upon the Circle of the Earth, and the Inhabitants thereof are as grashoppers;</hi> By his Spirit <hi>he will remove the great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Earth, and they shall become a Plain, and he will bring forth the Head-stone, and lay it a top of all; for the stone which is cut out of the Mountain without hands, breaks in pieces the Image, and will become a great Mountain, and the Kingdom which shall never be destroyed, (and shall not be left to other people, but will break in pieces, and consume all Kingdoms) this is arising, and the Ancient of Dayes is coming to sit in Judgement in the Saints of the Most High; and the Kingdomes of the world is becoming the Kingdomes of the Lord and of his Christ; and the little one shall become a thousand, and the small one a great Nation. Dan</hi> 7. <hi>chap.</hi> And the Lord of Hosts will hasten it in his time; so it is in vain to stand against the God of Heaven, or to resist his work which he hath begun in the Earth, which he is working, and will work by his Spirit, in this his day of Power he wil make all his people willing and subject to him, <hi>&amp; every knee must bow to him, and every tongue confess to God; for the first Adam was made a living soul, but the second is the Lord from Heaven, a quickning spirit which doth quicken and raise up the just unto the resurrection of Life, and he is made manifest in his people to destroy the works of the Devil,</hi> which he hath wrought in the disobedient part of man, and so brought the first <hi>Adam</hi> into the fall, and so under the Curse, that the very Earth is cursed for his sake; but <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> which the <hi>Apostle saw made a little lower then Angels; for the suffering of death, through which he hath wrought the Redemption of man Heb.</hi> 2.6. into a blessed, and happy, &amp; perfect condition; Though the Priests and Teachers of the World makes it their Work to destroy this Work of Redemption of the Son of God, <hi>who redeems out of sin and all evil, and from a vain Conversation, to serve the living God in newness of spirit, and not in the oldness of the letter, which redeems from the Earth, and from the pollutions of the world, and from all unrighteousness, all those that believe on him, and trust in him, and obey him, and wait for him, unto them shall he come the second time without sin unto sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104408:11"/>but this is a Mystery, which cannot be believed, by the dark and ignorant sinning and transgressing Ministry and Professors of the Nations, which lyes wallowing in their sins and uncleanness, <hi>and drink up iniquity as the Ox drinketh Water;</hi> these that are filling up their measure of iniquity, and are wholly covered with the power of darkness, these cannot see how it is possible that ever any should get out of this state and condition, being that they are quite ignorant of their Redeemer living in them, and so goes about to perswade all people of an impossibility of being freed from sin, but that they must sin all the dayes of their lives, and so keeps peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the fall, in the transgression, under the curse, &amp; death is the reward of sin; and so these Ministers are the Ministers of death: But Christ Jesus redeems from under the Curse, and from under the Bondage of sin and corruption, which all the Creation hath long groaned under, &amp; waits for the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed liberty of the Sons and Children of God, <hi>Glory &amp; honour be unto his holy Name for ever, who hath sent his only begotten Son in the likeness of sinful flesh, and for sin, condemned sin the flesh; for as by one man's disobedience many were made sinners, so by the obedience of one, shall many be made righteous:</hi> But this the disobedient will never know, who turns from, and disobeys the one that should make them righteous: And here are all the Priests and Teachers, and Professors of the world, in the disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, erred from the Spirit, in the Transgression, and in the sin; and so teaching all people to be sinners, as they can do no otherwise, who are not Ministers of the Light of Christ, nor turns not people to the Light of Christ, in whom is no sin, who hath said, <hi>Except a man be born again of water and of the spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Now that which is born of the Spirit, is Spirit, and this enters the Kingdom; <hi>For it is the spirit that quickens, the flesh profiteth nothing; The words that I speak unto you,</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>they are spirit, and they are life;</hi> but there were some that believed not: Now those that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Light of the Spirit of Life, they know little of the pourings forth of the Spirit, or of the Manifestation of the Spirit of God, which he hath given to every one to profit withall; but the Ministers of the Letter, and of darknesse,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104408:11"/>which have erred from the Spirit, and endeavours to keep all people back from the teaching, and leading, and guiding of the Spirit, they do not profit with it, but hides their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the Earth, and counts the Lord a hard Master; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he must needs take it from them, and give it unto those that have profited with it; this is witnessed, and manifested, and seen with those that have eyes in this day; <hi>The Apostles spake as the Spirit gave them utterance,</hi> and their preaching was <hi>not with the enticing words of mans wisdom, but in the power and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration of the Spirit, not according to the wisdom of the world; but he spake the wisdom of God in a Mystery, even the hidden wisdom which God had revealed unto him by his Spirit, which Spirit search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth all things, yea the deep things of God.</hi> Therefore its good for every one to have a true Testimony of this Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; <hi>which believes not every spirit, but tryes them, whether they be of God, and proves all things, and holds fast that which is good;</hi> and he that layes his Foundation here, he builds not his House <hi>on</hi> the <hi>Sand,</hi> but on the <hi>Rock, on which the whole Church is built, which is in God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, and Pillar and Ground of Truth; And when the wind blows, the storms and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests beats, this House will stand; for they that are joyned to the Lord, are one Spirit with him, and of one heart and soul;</hi> if they were ten thousand, they are all one, and all of one, who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and born, and brought forth, and sanctified by one Spirit; and here is the Mystery of the fellowship of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, <hi>which is in the unity of the Spirit, which is the bond of peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is not a shaddow, nor a vanishing fading thing; but this is a substance that proceeds from the living God, and returns unto him; by which Spirit he is made known unto the sons of men, and by which spirit he works and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates in Christ Jesus unto Righteousness and true Holiness; <hi>For by one Spirit we are all baptized into one Body, who have been made to drink all into one Spirit, whether Jews or Gentiles, Bond or Free;</hi> if they come into this Spirit which makes, and unites, and knits together, they are all one; <hi>for the body is not one member, but many;</hi> but they that denies this Spirit, and the teaching thereof, are not of this body, nor do not drink of this Cup of the New-Testament; but they are drinking of the Cup
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104408:12"/>of Fornication and Idolatry; for the Apostle said, <hi>They could not sit at the Lords Table, and the Table of Devils; and they could not drink the Cup of the Lord, and the Cup of Devils;</hi> and so they that drink not of the Cup of the Spirit <hi>[new]</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, let them read in their own bosomes what they are drinking of.</p>
            <p>The Apostle said, That the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were manifestly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared <hi>to be the Epistle of Christ ministred by him; written not with Ink, but with the Spirit of the living God; not in Tables of stone, but in the fleshly Tables of the heart.</hi> Here is the Ministration mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested by them that are Ministers of the Spirit of the living God, who reach unto that of God in the hearts of people; and the same Spirit in people answers to <hi>the annointing which is in them, which they received, even the Unction of the holy One;</hi> and such <hi>need not that any man should teach them, but as the same annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting teacheth them, which is truth, and no lye,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.27. But this is not the Ministration of the Letter, but of the Spirit; <hi>for the Letter killeth, but the Spirit giveth life,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. For the Apostle was made an able Minister of the New Testament, whose Ministration was more glorious then the Law, which was written in Tables of stone; and he saith, <hi>The Lord is the Spirit,</hi> which Spirit is <hi>written in the fleshly Tables of the heart, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty, and all that are the Sons of God, are led and guided by the spirit of God,</hi> Rom. 8. According to the Apostles words, who said, <hi>Because ye are sons, God hath sent forth the spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying Abba, Father,</hi> Gal. 4.6. <hi>And we through the spirit, wait for the hope of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness by Faith and who walks and abides in the spirit, doth not fulfil the lusts of the flesh; for the flesh lusteth against the spirit, and the spirit against the flesh, and these are contrary the one to the other,</hi> Gal. 5.5. And this is the Teacher, Leader and Guider of God's People, <hi>who are called to be Saints, &amp; sanctified in Christ Iesus, through the obedience of the spirit which subdues, &amp; brings down, &amp; subjecteth under in man and woman, that which is contrary;</hi> it working and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the inward man, and putting on, and adorning the <hi>heart with a meek, and with a quiet spirit, which is with the Lord of great price:</hi> This is precious in the fight of the Lord, when the Spirit beautifies with salvation, and sanctifies the heart
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104408:12"/>to the Lord by its powerful working, here the Lord is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his Saints; and this eternal Spirit, and Substance, and Word, <hi>which is quick and powerful, sharper then any two-edged Sword, which separates betwixt the precious and the vile, betwixt the holy and profane, piercing to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit, and of the ioynts and marrow, and is a discerner of the thoughts and intents of the heart, Heb.</hi> 4.12. This is the sure Teacher that layeth <hi>a true Foundation,</hi> on which the Prophets and Apostles are built, <hi>the Corner-stone, which all the wise Builders have disal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and set at nought, which is now become the Head of our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; glory &amp; honor be to the Highest for ever,</hi> according to Christs words, who saith, <hi>Did you not read in the Scripture, The Stone which all the Builders rejected and set at nought, the same is become the Head of the Corner; this is the Lords doings, and is marvelous in our eyes; and whosoever shall fall on this stone, shall be broken; but on whomsoever it shall fall, it will grind him to powder, Matth.</hi> 21.42, 49. And <hi>Peter</hi> saith, <hi>That it is contained in the Scripture, Behold, I lay in Sion a chief Corner-store, elect and precious; and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on him, shall not be confounded;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Isa.</hi> 28 16 <hi>Psal.</hi> 118.22. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6, 7 8.</note>
               <hi>unto you therefore which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he is precious; but unto them who are disobedient, the Stone which the Builders disallowed, the same is made the Head of the Corner, and stone of stumbling, and a Rock of offence,</hi> even to them that stumble at the Word, being disobedient; this is the Stone and Word that all the disobedient stumbles at; <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> that will not come to the Light which Christ Jesus (who is the light of men) hath enlightened them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; the obedience of the Light of Christ Jesus, is the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Cross of Christ, the preaching of which (the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle saith) it was to the <hi>Jews a stumbling-block, and to the Greeks foolishness; but unto all, both Jews and Greeks, it is Christ the Power of God, and the wisdom of God;</hi> 1 Cor. 1. The Light and the Power of God, is the Cross of Christ; this the Apostle did not preach with the wisdom of Words, <hi>least the Crosse of Christ should become of none effect,</hi> which is unto all that are sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Power of God; and he saith, <hi>After that in the wisdom of God, the world by wisdom knew not God, it pleased God by the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishness of Preaching, to save them that believe:</hi> This is the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and the Way of God, not to teach people by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104408:13"/>that which man's Wisdom teacheth; and that which man's dark heart invents and imagines, &amp; studies out of his brain, but by that which the Holy Ghost teacheth in this his day in which he is risen in his Eternal Spirit; and they that can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in this foolishness of preaching, are saved; and they that <hi>cannot believe,</hi> to them this <hi>Gospel</hi> is hid, because that the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishness of God is wiser then men, and the weakness of God is stronger then men, who hath said, <hi>I will destroy the wisdom of the wise, and bring to nought the understanding of the prudent; for God hath chosen the foolish things of the world, to confound the things that are mighty, that no flesh might glory in his presence, but in him:</hi> This is the Will, and Way, and Work of the Lord, by which he teacheth his people, and so <hi>they have access by one spirit unto God the Father, Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Barbarians, Scithians, Bond</hi> and <hi>Free</hi> if they come unto Christ Jesus the Light and Life, and everlasting Covenant, <hi>which is given to be the salvation unto the ends of the Earth, which was offered up by the Eternal Spirit once for all. Eph.</hi> 2.18.</p>
            <p>All people which comes unto this Eternal Spirit which is <hi>in them,</hi> of what sort soever, if they come to this Light, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and Spirit, they are all one in <hi>Christ Jesus, and if they be Christs, then are they Abrahams Seeds, and Heirs according to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise.</hi> All that doth endeavour to keep the Unity in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and Bond of Peace, is strengthened by this Spirit in the Inner-man; &amp; the eyes of their Understanding comes to be enlightened, &amp; they do come to comprehend with all Saints, the heigth, and the breadth, and the depth of the love of God, which passeth knowledge, and is a mystery to the wise <hi>Rabbies</hi> of the World, and all the disobedient ones, that will not stoop to the Light of Christ, and his Power &amp; cross in them, but will live in the liberty of the flesh, where they may exercise their fleshly liberty, Pride and Ambition, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of Naughtiness, vain Glory and Arrogancy, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuousness, Pomp and Vanity of the World, all which are of the first man, fallen from God, and is of the Earth, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which the cross of Christ, which is the power of God is to crucifie the affections and the lusts thereof, the World, and the flesh, and the Devil, who is obedient and faithful to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104408:13"/>Witness and Testimony of the living God <hi>in them,</hi> and to its <hi>Guiding,</hi> and <hi>Leading,</hi> and <hi>Teaching;</hi> puts off the old man and his deeds, and puts on the <hi>new man, Christ Jesus, who is created after God in righteousness and true holiness, and so comes to be renewed in the spirit of their minds, and to have their conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cleansed, and their bodies washed with pure water, Eph.</hi> 5. And so they bring forth the fruits of the spirit, which are <hi>in all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, righteousness, and truth,</hi> yea, <hi>joy, love, peace, long suffering, gentleness, faith, meekness, and temperance;</hi> And against such <hi>there is no Law;</hi> who are in this state, <hi>keeps the Law,</hi> and <hi>breaks it not,</hi> and are <hi>in the Love,</hi> which <hi>fulfils it,</hi> and one with the <hi>Justice, Equity,</hi> and <hi>Righteousness</hi> of it, <hi>which was added because of transgression: And where there is no transgression, there is no need of a Law, nor the Law is not against such.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we finde little of those fruits of the Spirit in the World (which cannot receive the Spirit of Truth) amongst all <hi>Professors, Priests</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> thereof; this is the Mark which Christ hath set us to try the false Prophets by; he saith, <hi>By their fruits shall you know them,</hi> who gets the <hi>sheeps clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> (the Scriptures) <hi>but inwardly are ravening wolves:</hi> We have found the <hi>Priests, Professors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> of these Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to minister <hi>Persecution</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> to us, as the <hi>Prisons</hi> and <hi>Goals</hi> of these Nations may bear (and have born) <hi>testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi> And another Mark that Christ gave of the false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to know them by, was, <hi>when all men should speak well of them, for so did their Fathers of the false Prophets:</hi> Now let all people judge, whether this be not the condition of the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> at this day; <hi>for they bear rule by their means, and yet the people love to have it so; but what will they do in the end thereof, when God comes with his overflowing scourge, and breaks the Covenant with Death, and the agreement with Hell, and sweep away the Refuge of Lyes Matth.</hi> 7. Which many hundreds of years have bin their strength; but God is coming to overturn them, &amp; to confound them, &amp; to cut down the fruitless trees that brings not forth good fruit, and doth manifest that the evil Tree cannot bring forth good fruit; <hi>for men do not gather Grapes of Thorns, nor Figs of Thistles;</hi> for the best of them have been but as a <hi>Bryar,</hi> &amp; the most upright of them as a <hi>Thorn-Hedge,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:104408:14"/>as many will come to see when their eyes comes to be opened; and they shall be as <hi>a bowed wall,</hi> and as <hi>a tottering fence, Psal.</hi> 62. Let but the honest and the godly hearted judge betwixt them and us, whether their fruits are not the fruits of the flesh, which the Apostle saith (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.) are these, <hi>Adultery, Fornication, Uncleanness, Laesciviousness, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Witchcraft, Hatred, Variance, Emulation, Wrath, Strife, Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Heresies, Envyings, Murthers, Drunkenness, Revilings, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate affections, evil Concupiscence, Covetousness which is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Anger, Malice, Blasphemy, filthy Communication, Effeminate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and abusers of themselves with mankind, Revellings, Banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Excesse of Wine,</hi> and <hi>abominable Idolaters, Filthinesse, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish jesting and talking which is not convenient, Col.</hi> 3.8. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9. And let the upright judge, whether they be not <hi>lovers of themselves, covetous boasters, proud blasphemers, unthankful, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, disobedient to Parents, without natural affection, truce-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, false Accusers, Incontinent, fierce despisers of them that are good, heady, high-minded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God, having a form of godliness, but denying the Power, and from such</hi> (the Apostle exhorts the people to) <hi>turn away,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Reader</hi> may judge it to be harsh, or censorious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in charging all these fruits of the flesh upon the <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Ministers</hi> of the World, many of which they would seem to evade; but this I say further for the Information of the <hi>Reader,</hi> that they are <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>Darknesse,</hi> and not <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> but denyes the <hi>Light,</hi> both to <hi>Minister from,</hi> and to <hi>Minister to;</hi> which the Ministers of God were <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> and the Message that they brought, was, <hi>That God was Light, and in him was no darknesse at all,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.1. And <hi>Paul was made an able Minister of the New-Testament, not of the Letter, but of the Spirit;</hi> and he <hi>turned People from the darknesse to the light, and from the power of Satan unto God, who is light,</hi> in which <hi>whosoever walks, the blood of Jesus Christ his Son, cleanseth him from all sin.</hi> Now these <hi>Ministers</hi> &amp; <hi>Teachers</hi> of the World, whose <hi>Ministry</hi> stands in the <hi>darkness</hi> where all sin is committed, and all the fruits of the flesh acted, these cannot clear themselves from none of the things before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for they stand in that ground which brings forth the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104408:14"/>fruits of the flesh; and therefore is their Doctrine altogether <hi>for sin,</hi> and <hi>against perfection</hi> and <hi>cleansing,</hi> and <hi>preacheth frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> that none can <hi>be free from sin while they are upon the Earth;</hi> for they are guilty in their hearts and consciences, that they sin continually, &amp; so with their blind dark minds they can never see that any can be cleansed or redeemed from sin, which is wholly contrary to the <hi>Apostles Doctrine,</hi> who saith, <hi>That Christ was manifest to take away sin, whosoever abideth in him, sinneth not; whosoever sinneth, hath not seen him, neither known him; he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth sin is of the Devil; whosoever is born of God, doth not commit sin, for his Seed remaineth in him, and he cannot sin, because he is born of God;</hi> in this is <hi>the children of God manifest, and the children of the Devil,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. And now <hi>Reader,</hi> do but in soberness weigh those things according to the truth of the Scriptures, &amp; this will take away the prejudice, &amp; remove the Objection which might arise in thy mind concerning the fruits of the flesh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Professors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all that desires after godliness, &amp; the Truth as it is <hi>in Jesus,</hi> they must turn from them that hath the <hi>Form,</hi> &amp; denies the <hi>Power,</hi> who brings forth the fruits before-mentioned; <hi>for as many as receives Christ Jesus,</hi> (the Light) <hi>to them he gives power to become the Sons of God.</hi> It is the word of his Power by which all things were created, by which he upholds all things; and it is his power that brings his Seed out of Bondage, &amp; out of the house of darkness: And the <hi>Gospel</hi> of our <hi>Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> which the <hi>Apostle</hi> was not ashamed of to preach, <hi>is the power of God unto salvation, unto every one that believes, to the Jew first, &amp; also to the Greek; and this Treasure the Apostle had in an earthen vessel, that the excellency of the Power might be of God:</hi> And here was the Apostles Doctrine established, in the mighty power of God, <hi>whereof</hi> (saith he) <hi>I was made a Minister according to the gift of the Grace of God given unto me, by the effectual working of his Power, that so he might know the power of his resurrection, and the fellowship of his sufferings:</hi> but this is a <hi>Mystery,</hi> and unknown to the <hi>Teachers</hi> &amp; <hi>Ministers</hi> of the <hi>letter,</hi> who are in <hi>forms</hi> &amp; <hi>appearances,</hi> without the <hi>Power,</hi> &amp; in the ordinations of <hi>men,</hi> &amp; receives their approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>from men</hi> &amp; are made <hi>Ministers</hi> by <hi>men,</hi> these deny and resist the <hi>Power</hi> &amp; <hi>Spirit</hi> the <hi>Apostles</hi> were made <hi>Ministers</hi> of, &amp; even denies <hi>immediate Revelation,</hi> &amp; saith <hi>it is ceased,</hi> &amp; so denies the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104408:15"/>gift of Gods grace <hi>which hath appeared unto all men, to teach the denying of ungodliness &amp; all worldly lusts, &amp; teacheth</hi> (all that doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, &amp; follow it) <hi>to live godly, righteously, &amp; soberly in this present evil world.</hi> And so those <hi>Teachers</hi> endeavours to <hi>limit</hi> the spirit of the living God to <hi>Times</hi> &amp; <hi>Persons,</hi> which cannot be <hi>limited;</hi> and saith, we must not look for it <hi>now,</hi> as in the <hi>Apostles time;</hi> we must look to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> &amp; not to the <hi>Spirit</hi> for Revelation; &amp; so <hi>blasphemes</hi> the God of Heaven, &amp; <hi>gainsays</hi> his Truth, &amp; the <hi>revelation</hi> of the Son of God, who said, <hi>The Father was a Spirit, &amp; they that worship him, must worship him in spirit &amp; in truth, &amp; he was seeking for such worshippers to worship him,</hi> &amp; who hath said, <hi>There is none that knows the Son but the Father, neither doth any man know the Father save the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so these <hi>Teachers</hi> that <hi>denies Revelation,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Spirits tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> doth not desire that the <hi>Son</hi> should be known by the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drawing; for there is none that can come to the Son, except the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draw him;</hi> neither is it possible for them to bring people to the knowledg of the <hi>Father</hi> who denies <hi>Revelation,</hi> being <hi>there is none that knows the Father save the Son, &amp; he to whom the Son reveals him;</hi> so the infinite mercy &amp; wisdom of the Lord God hath hid these things from them, &amp; hath revealed them unto the <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> &amp; <hi>obedient,</hi> who walks in his <hi>Light,</hi> &amp; keeps in it, where the <hi>revelation</hi> is manifested; &amp; so <hi>Christ Iesus</hi> saw great cause of <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Lord of Heaven and Earth, that he had hid those things from the wise &amp; prudent, &amp; had revealed them unto Babes,</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the <hi>Light,</hi> which were begotten into the <hi>Light,</hi> &amp; were <hi>translated</hi> into it, &amp; made one with it, &amp; abode in the <hi>Annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> which they received in the beginning, <hi>they had fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with the Son &amp; with the Father; he that believes on the Son, hath everlasting life; he that believeth not on the Son, shall not see life; for the Father loveth the Son, &amp; sheweth him all things that he doth;</hi> For as the <hi>Father</hi> raiseth up the dead, &amp; quickneth them, even so the <hi>Son</hi> quickneth whom he will; &amp; who believes in the <hi>Light,</hi> and walks in the light of the Son of God, is quickned by him, &amp; hath the <hi>Father</hi> revealed to him, not in <hi>Parables,</hi> but he doth shew him plainly of the <hi>Father;</hi> for he hath committed <hi>all judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the <hi>Son,</hi> that all men might honor the <hi>Son,</hi> as they honor the <hi>Father;</hi> he that <hi>honoreth</hi> not the <hi>Son,</hi> honoreth not the <hi>Father</hi> that hath sent him; he that believeth not <hi>in the light of the Son
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104408:15"/>of God,</hi> he honoreth not the <hi>Son;</hi> &amp; he whose mind is not tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>unto the Light</hi> of God <hi>in him,</hi> he knows not the <hi>Son,</hi> nor <hi>him</hi> that <hi>sent him;</hi> Jesus cryed and said, <hi>He that believeth on me, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not on me, but on him that sent me; he that seeth me, seeth him that sent me. I am come a Light into the World, that whosoever belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth on me, should not abide in darkness:</hi> Mark here now, Christ's Words; He that sees him <hi>to be the light come into the world,</hi> sees him <hi>that sent him;</hi> &amp; he that believes in Christ <hi>that is come a light into the world,</hi> believes <hi>on him</hi> that <hi>sent him;</hi> and he that believes on Christ Jesus <hi>who is come a Light into the world,</hi> abides not <hi>in the darkness, but hath the Light of life;</hi> this is the great Work of God that every one believe on him that God hath sent; &amp; he that believeth on him, <hi>hath the witness and testimony of him in himself;</hi> &amp; he that knows not that <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>in him,</hi> is a <hi>Reprobate; And this is the will of him that sent me</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>that every one that seeth the Son, may have everlasting life, &amp; I will raise him up at the last Day:</hi> This is the portion and reward which the true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers receive from him <hi>who is the resurrection and the life, he that believes on him, though he was dead, yet shall he live, and he that lives and believes, shall never dye; (He that can receive it, let him.)</hi> This was a <hi>Mystery</hi> unto <hi>Martha:</hi> Jesus saith, <hi>No man can come unto me except the Father (which hath sent me) draw him; It is written in the Prophets</hi> (saith he) <hi>They shall be all taught of God; every man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that hath heard, and hath learned of the Father, cometh unto me.</hi> So here now every one whose eye is single, may see, <hi>that none can come</hi> but <hi>whom the Father draws,</hi> and they that are <hi>taught of God,</hi> comes to the <hi>Son, which he hath given a light into the world;</hi> and this is the <hi>WAY,</hi> the <hi>TRUTH,</hi> and the <hi>LIFE;</hi> &amp; no man comes to the <hi>Father</hi> but by <hi>him;</hi> And in no <hi>other way,</hi> nor by no <hi>other Name</hi> under Heaven <hi>shall any one be saved,</hi> but <hi>by him, and he is able to save to the utmost all those that comes unto God by him, and no other Foundation can any man lay, then this which is already laid;</hi> but let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one take heed how he builds thereon; &amp; he which <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth another Gospel, let him be accurst;</hi> For this is the <hi>Rock</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> on which the whole <hi>Church</hi> is built, <hi>CHRIST IESUS</hi> the <hi>LIGHT,</hi> and precious Stone, which <hi>Iews</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentiles</hi> that are saved, are built on; for he is their Peace <hi>who hath made both one, and hath broken down the middle wall of Partition which was between, for through him we have doth an access to the Father, &amp; are built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104408:16"/>the Foundation of the Apostles and Prophets, JESUS CHRIST himself being the chief Corner-stone, in whom all the Building fitly fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med together, groweth unto a holy people in the Lord, who are builded to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for an habitation of God, through the spirit;</hi> Here is the great Work of the Mystery of God, which he is working in this his day, <hi>whose Tabernacle is with men,</hi> and the Most High dwells in <hi>the Kingdoms of men,</hi> he whose delight is with the sons of men, is arisen, and wisdom lifteth up her voice, and cries, <hi>Oh ye</hi> simple ones, <hi>understand wisdom; &amp; ye</hi> fools, <hi>be of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding heart; unto you,</hi> O men, <hi>I call, and my voice is to the</hi> Sons of men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRIST JESUS</hi> is coming <hi>to reign, &amp; the Scepter of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness which is a right Scepter, will he sway the Nations with; &amp; those his enemies that will not that he should reign, must even be broke, and bound, and slain before him;</hi> therefore it is good for all people to hear his voice, and to turn at his reproof, and to hearken dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to <hi>the Word that is nigh in the heart,</hi> &amp; to encline <hi>their ears</hi> that <hi>their souls</hi> might <hi>live;</hi> there is a Word that saith, <hi>This is the way;</hi> which way is for the way faring man; <hi>This TEACHER will never more be removed into a corner; but their eyes must see their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher;</hi> this <hi>WAY</hi> which hath long been <hi>hid</hi> and <hi>hedged</hi> up, Now hath the Lord <hi>opened</hi> and made manifest in this <hi>his Day,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Testimony</hi> which was sealed among the <hi>Disciples, is now opened,</hi> and the Word that speaks according to the Light <hi>is now revealed,</hi> &amp; the Light is shining in the consciences of men, and they that are children of the Light, and of the Day, walks in it, <hi>and it shines in their hearts, and gives them the light of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ, the express Image of the Invisible God, the first-born of every creature;</hi> And this <hi>cleanseth</hi> and <hi>purgeth the conscience from dead works, to serve the living God;</hi> &amp; in this every one may draw near in full assurance of Faith, <hi>having their hearts sprinkled from an evil conscience, and their bodies washed with pure water;</hi> but it was impossible that the <hi>blood of Buls</hi> and <hi>Goats</hi> should <hi>take away sin;</hi> but this man <hi>after he had offered one sacrifice for sin, sate down at the right hand of God, expecting till his enemies be made his footstool;</hi> Which the <hi>high Priests</hi> that went before him, were daily offring the same Sacrifice which could never <hi>take away sin,</hi> nor <hi>make perfect as appertaining to the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> yet <hi>by one offering, Christ Iesus the everlasting High Priest, hath
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104408:16"/>perfected for ever them that are sanctified;</hi> this is he that doth the will, who said, <hi>In the volume of thy Book it is written of me, Lo I come to do thy will, O God;</hi> by which Wil we are sanctified, whereof the Holy Ghost is a witness to us; for after that he said before, <hi>This is the Covenant that I wil make with them, After these days</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>I will put my Law in their hearts, and in their minds, I will write them;</hi> Here the <hi>Apostle</hi> witnesseth the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> to be the <hi>Witness</hi> &amp; <hi>Testimony</hi> of Gods truth in the <hi>promise</hi> of the <hi>new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> written <hi>in the heart,</hi> &amp; of the <hi>spirit</hi> putting in <hi>the inward parts;</hi> Now these that denies <hi>the spirit</hi> of God which gives testimony and witness of his everlasting Covenant, are strangers <hi>to this life,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aliens</hi> to the <hi>Common wealth</hi> of <hi>Israel;</hi> for the Covenant of Promise is to the <hi>elect Seed</hi> of <hi>Abraham;</hi> not of the <hi>Bond-woman,</hi> but of the <hi>Free;</hi> not of the <hi>SEEDS,</hi> which are <hi>many,</hi> but of <hi>ONE,</hi> which is <hi>CHRIST, that is Elect according to the fore-knowledge of God the Father, through sanctification of the spirit, unto obedience, &amp; sprinkling of the blood of Christ, who doth purifie their souls in obeying the Truth, through the spirit;</hi> For this cause is the Gospel preached, that they may be judg'd according <hi>to men</hi> in the <hi>flesh,</hi> but live according <hi>to God</hi> in the <hi>spirit;</hi> this is the chief <hi>end</hi> of the <hi>Ministry</hi> of the <hi>GOSPEL, which is GLAD-TYDINGS to the Poor, LIBERTY to the Captive, but JUDGEMENT to him that hath captivated the Seed,</hi> till <hi>that</hi> be <hi>dead</hi> which hath held the Seed <hi>in bondage;</hi> and until the <hi>enmity</hi> be <hi>slain,</hi> and the <hi>middle wall</hi> of Partition <hi>taken away,</hi> and of <hi>twain,</hi> made <hi>one new man;</hi> this is the <hi>Ministration</hi> of the <hi>everlasting Gospel;</hi> for Christ also hath once suffered, being put to death <hi>in the flesh,</hi> but quickned <hi>in the spirit,</hi> by which also he went and preached unto the spirits in prison; &amp; he that is annointed <hi>to preach glad tydings to the poor, and liberty to the Captives, is now preaching to the spirits in prison, &amp; binding up the broken hearted,</hi> and raising up them <hi>that are fallen;</hi> and he is <hi>enlightning</hi> the <hi>blind eyes,</hi> and <hi>unstopping</hi> the <hi>deaf ears,</hi> &amp; <hi>opening the Prison-doors,</hi> and <hi>bringing the Prisoners forth of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son-houses, so that the Prisoners of hope doth rejoice, that have been in the pit which is without water;</hi> For Christ calls, <hi>Come unto me every one that is weary and heavy laden, &amp; they shall find rest for their souls,</hi> who will take his <hi>yoake</hi> upon them, <hi>which is easie,</hi> &amp; <hi>his burthen,</hi> which <hi>is light,</hi> to the <hi>obedient,</hi> and to the <hi>faithful,</hi> which are sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>unto him,</hi> &amp; <hi>waits</hi> for <hi>him,</hi> they that <hi>love him</hi> and keep <hi>his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104408:17"/>Commandments,</hi> who saith, <hi>He that hath my Commandments, &amp; keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, he it is that loveth me; &amp; he that loveth me, shall be loved of my Father, &amp; I will love him, &amp; will manifest my self unto him:</hi> Here is an Infinite reward, which wil even satisfie the <hi>Eternal</hi> &amp; <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal soul,</hi> which nothing <hi>can satisfie</hi> but <hi>the living God,</hi> who saith, <hi>If any love me, &amp; keep my words, my Father will love him and we shall come unto him, &amp; make our abode with him;</hi> Here the <hi>COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORTER,</hi> which is the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> which proceeds from the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> &amp; the <hi>Son,</hi> is manifested, <hi>which doth teach all things, &amp; brings all things to remembrance;</hi> &amp; this is <hi>the Inheritance which the Saints in Light are made partakers of,</hi> even <hi>the spirit of Truth</hi> which the world <hi>cannot receive,</hi> which leads <hi>into all truth all them</hi> which <hi>do obey</hi> and <hi>follow</hi> the <hi>leading,</hi> &amp; <hi>guiding,</hi> &amp; <hi>teaching</hi> of <hi>it:</hi> The <hi>Apostle</hi> desired that <hi>Timothy</hi> might know <hi>how he ought to behave himself in the house of God,</hi> which <hi>is the Church of the living God, the pillar and ground of Truth; And without controversie</hi> (saith he) <hi>great is the Mystery of godliness, GOD MANIFEST IN THE FLESH, usti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the spirit, seen of Angels, &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>mystery</hi> I have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in part to open, according to the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> And if any come to the <hi>Key of DAVID</hi> which opens this <hi>mystery,</hi> they will see the <hi>Truth</hi> of it, and seal to it in that measure of the Spirit which God hath given to every one to profit withall; <hi>For unto every one of us is given grace according to the measure of the gift of Christ, according to the good pleasure of his will; and he that is faithful in the little, is made Ruler over much:</hi> And so this is the <hi>WAY,</hi> the <hi>TRUTH,</hi> and the <hi>LIFE;</hi> and every one that doth set at nought this, and resist this, let <hi>his blood</hi> be upon <hi>his own head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let the <hi>Reader</hi> by what is here written, seriously search, examine, and try by the Scriptures, and the measure of the Spirit of God in him, who are the <hi>true Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>false;</hi> and who are the <hi>true Teachers,</hi> and who are the <hi>false,</hi> and what is the true Worship of God, and the false; And let him ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his soul, as he dare answer before a <hi>just</hi> &amp; <hi>Righteous God.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>From a true Lover of the souls of all people, and who desires the good of all, and that all might come to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> M. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104408:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>